[Music]
In a video I did a decade ago, you can
tell how ancient it is by these silly
graphics, I explained that the
cholesterol-raising factor in coffee
does not pass through a drip coffee
paper filter. Give people French press
coffee, which is filtered but without
paper, and their cholesterol swells up
over time starting within just 2 weeks.
But switch them to paper-filtered coffee
and their cholesterol comes right back
down. Same amount of coffee, but just
prepared differently.
The cholesterol-raising factor from
coffee beans has since been identified.
It's the It's the fatty substances in
the oil within coffee beans.
One reason it took us so long to figure
that out is that it didn't raise
cholesterol in rats, or hamsters, or
even monkeys, but it did in human
beings.
But it apparently gets stuck in the
paper filter. This explains why filtered
coffee doesn't affect cholesterol,
whereas boiled or French press or
Turkish coffees do. Espresso as well,
which has 20 times more of the
cholesterol-raising substance cafestol
than paper-filtered drip coffee, with
Turkish and boiled coffee being the
worst. Though instant and percolator
coffee are pretty low even without the
paper filter.
Note, if you make drip coffee with one
of those metal mesh filters without the
paper, it would presumably be just as
bad as like French press.
So the studies in general appear to
consistently find that it was this fatty
component that was then filtered out by
paper.
But a small number of studies suggested
that filtered coffee may also increase
cholesterol levels and began to cast
some doubt into what appeared to be a
fairly clear picture.
So yeah, the cholesterol-raising effects
brought about by the consumption of
filtered coffee may not be as strong as
that of boiled coffee. Maybe we
shouldn't discard the possibility that
filtered coffee may also play a small
but important role in raising
cholesterol. I knew about this study
where three cups a day filtered coffee
raised total cholesterol, but the rise
in LDL bad cholesterol was not
statistically significant. Same with
this study where stopping filtered
coffee reduced total cholesterol,
suggesting perhaps only partial removal.
But no one had ever just measured the
levels of the cholesterol-raising
compounds in the paper filters
until now. The results showed that most
of the cholesterol-raising cafestol was
retained by the coffee grounds, rather
than actually getting stuck in the
filter itself. In other words, the
principal function of the paper filter
is not necessarily to block the compound
itself, but to block any fine particles
that are carrying the compound. Like
when you make French press coffee,
there's that fine mesh screen, but you
still notice a little sludge at the
bottom of the cup. That's the tiny
particles that pass through and can
carry some of the risk.
But a little cafestol does get through
the filter. So yeah, I mean, you can cut
out more than 90% switching from French
press or one of the metal mesh filters
by using a paper filter. If you use
coffee that starts out with a high level
of the cafestol compound, you're still
clearing out about 95% with the paper,
but there may be enough left
to still bump your LDL. But you don't
know until you put it to the test. They
started out with a high cafestol coffee.
After a month of drinking two cups a
day, their LDL cholesterol went up
significantly, even though it was
paper-filtered.
So if you have high cholesterol despite
eating a healthy diet, you may want to
try cutting out coffee and getting
retested.
Or you can try switching to a lower
cafestol coffee. There's all sorts of
variables such as roasting degree or
grind size that may affect cafestol
levels. One can imagine a smaller
particle size would allow for greater
extraction.
Roasting appears to destroy some of it,
so a really dark roast should have less,
but there's not much difference between
just like light and medium roast. And
indeed, in this study, there was no
significant difference between the rise
in cholesterol after a medium-light
roast versus a medium roast. They both
raised bad cholesterol.
[Music]